wooo-o-o-o-o-o-o-o-oh wha tta teeeee laa lee doo lee dee a-a-a o-o-o e-e-e
a-a-a-a-a...
ha-ha it's kinda pretty froggie started idt... wo-u-u-u-uh
Frog went a-kkkkk-courtin', and he did ride, kkkkkk-crambone
Frog went a-kkk-courtin', and he did ride.
With a sword and a pppf-ppf-pf-pp(pistol) revolver by his side. kkkkkk-crambone
crambo killed a-la-la-ra-ra-ro-r-ro-rooo-ffff-floppppa-dooodle tu-lla-dee tu-
la-dee...... thats a hard part right in there n-n-nephew....
crambo killed a-la-la-ra-ro floppppa-dooodle tu-lla dee raaap da kk-crambo...
aaaaaaa leeeeeee oohhhh layyy, heeeeeee!!!!! umhmmm!!! that yoodle goes right
in there somewhere, but it's a little to high for me!!!
ouhhhh
Where the wedding supper be? kkkkkk-crambone
Where the wedding supper be?
Way down yonder in a hek-on-a-ya hek-on-a-ya(hollow) inna-woo-woo enn-nee cat-
aa-e in the eucaliptus tree, crambo...
crambo killed a-la-la-ra-ra-ro-r-ro-rooo-ffff-floppppa-dooodle tu-lla-
dee...... thats a hard part again ran-in-o..ha-ha..
floppppa-dooodle tu-lla dee raaap da kk-crambo...