Frog went a-courtin' and a-he did a-ride. Hey, hey.
((Frogie went a-courtin' and a-he did ride, Hey, hey.))
((Frogie went a-courtin' and a-he did ride,))
Sword and a pistol by his side.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
Rode till he come to Miss Mouse's door. ((Hey, hey.))
((Rode till he come to Miss Mouse's door,))
Gave three raps and a barrel outroar.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
Said, "Miss Mouse, are you within? ((Hey, hey.))
Said, "Miss Mouse, are you within?"
"Yes, I just sat down to spin."
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
Well, he went a-right in an' took'er on his knee. Hey, hey.
((Went a-right in an' took'er on his knee. Hey, hey.))
Went a-right in an' took'er on his knee,
I'm set in this town, till yer marryin' me.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
Miss Mouse said, "I cain't answer that." ((Hey, hey.))
((Miss Mousie said, "I cain't answer that." Hey, hey.))
Miss Mouse said, "I cain't answer that,
Till I seen my brother, Rat.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
When a-brother, Rat, gave his consent... ((Hey, hey.))
((When brother, Rat, gave his consent... Hey, hey.))
When brother, Rat, gave his consent,
The weasel wrote the public 'vent.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
Who will the wedding guests all be? ((Hey, hey.))
((Who will the wedding guests all be? Hey, hey.))
Who will the wedding guests all be?
A lady bug and a bumble bee.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.)) (Woo!)
Hey, hey-hey, hey.
Well, the first to come was a little lady bug. ((Hey, hey.))
((First to come was a little lady bug. Hey, hey.))
First guest to come was a little lady bug,
She had a great big whiskey jug.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
Well, the next to come was a bumble bee. ((Hey, hey.))
((Next to come was a bumble bee. Hey, hey.))
Next to come was a bumble bee,
Dancin' a jig with a two-legged flea.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
First one to come was a little, bitty moth. ((Hey, hey.)) 7
((First one to come was a little, bitty moth. ((Hey, hey.))
First one to come was a little, bitty moth,
First one to lay the table cloth.
((Hey, hey-hey, hey.))
So, here’s the endin', a-one, two, three. ((Hey, hey.))
((Here’s the endin', a-one, two, three. Hey, hey.))
Here's the end with a-one, two, three,
A snake and a frog and a-Miss Mousie.
Hey, hey-hey, hey.