It's been an eventful journey for Polestar so far and not without obstacles,
but through determination, innovation and an obsession with detail,
We finally arrived at a very exciting stage.
VP, verification prototype build.
It's one thing to design a car that challenges existing norms,
while also raising the bar for electric cars the world over.
It's another thing entirely to realize that design in real life.
From aesthetics to driver experience,
no stone is left unturned during these builds.
The VP cars are the first build series and a major player in these prototype builds is carbon fiber.
Carbon fiber figures hugely in the Polestar1.
ten times stronger and five times lighter than steel.
Carbon fiber is the ideal material to realize the ambitious plans for this car
to make the body more rigid and therefore create more responsive handling.
The entire upper body of the Polestar1 is carbon fiber reinforced polymer.
but that's not all.
the true carbon fiber game changer is the dragonfly.
A CFRP patch bonded to the steel underbody to increase torsional stiffness by 45%.
The dragonfly, actually three parts,
the body and the wings glued into place and fired in the oven at 85 degrees for 45 minutes also strengthens this traditionally weak point.
The next stop is the hang on parts area,
where components are measured with unforgiving precision before they're attached.
The slightest of misalignments can cause a disruption of the feature lines,
thus compromising the Polestar1's distinctive design.
Working with carbon fiber, however, can present different challenges.
painting, for example,
carbon fiber substrates aren't smooth and free of imperfections like steel,
and they have a distinctive weave.
The solution,
a combination of machine sanding and hand sanding to give the panels a smooth, even finish
fine sanding is done by hand to ensure the integrity of the feature lines and to stay true to the initial design.
The marriage point is the true test of all this exacting measurement.
Where the chassis is attached to the body.
The parts are attached by a series of bolts protruding from the chassis,
which then slide into the upper body.
If even one of the bolts is misaligned
the process must begin again.
With every Union performed, the process goes more smoothly.
This means fewer adjustments and a shorter construction time
closer and closer to perfection with each marriage.
双语字幕：@PolestarX