It is about time I gave an answer to a question I have been asked a hundred times.
Where is the brand Polestar heading?
We brought the Polestar 1 into production and we launched the Polestar 2.
Now for us inside Polestar we have a clear vision of where we are going.
The answer is the Polestar Precept.
Precept is an incarnation of the philosophy of our design, of our idea about how sustainability
can become a driving force, a driving  energy for our new cars.
That is what Precept is all about.
A big focus, a strong focus is obviously an interior, that reduces the amount of
plastic that you use.
We work together with specialised partners and experts to cut the plastic content and
lessen waste materials with innovative natural and recycled source materials,
in the interior of the Polestar Precept.
With the amazing powerRibs and ampliTex technologies from our partner Bcomp,
we turn natural fibers into lightweight and sustainable interior panels.
This natural composite utilises flax and these new innovative interior panels then
are up to 50% lighter and they reduce the plastic content by 80% compared to the traditional ones.
It’s really amazing, it’s lighter and at the same time stronger.
Now on the seats we introduce 3D Knit material, like what is used in the fashion
or footwear industries.
It’s made out of 100% recycled yarn derived from PET, pet bottles.
It’s made exactly to size with no offcuts and that means we’ve completely removed
the waste in its production process.
So, to show that car interior can be the nice atmosphere that you want it to be,
without the usual use of an excessive amount of virgin plastic,
I think that is one of the main focus areas of Precept.
When we presented last year the Polestar 2 we were the first car brand coming out
with a production car that has Android.
Now that has incredible potential for the future, and some of it a gives
a glimpse of how great the system will evolve over time.
We take here in the Polestar Precept, example given, one that I actually like the most,
is the proximity sensor that we built in there.
You see an uncluttered, very easy to read aesthetically nice screen.
But then when you reach out, buttons pop out, and more information comes.
Big buttons that are easy to touch even when the car is moving.
So this animated proximity sensor is really a big big step into this hassle-free
future that we promise with our cars.
A big leap for safety in the car is the eye tracking system of the Precept.
One of the core benefits is monitoring the driver's health status.
Is he tired, is she watching the road?
If not, the car takes appropriate actions such as warning or speed reduction.
On the driver-dedicated monitor in front of you, the information
and signals of the pilot assist system are now combined with Google maps data.
So the turn-by-turn guidance is embedded into a fully contextualised navigation.
Where black holes for air intakes and cooling define the era of combustion engines,
the face of the Polestar is characterised and defined by the SmartZone
where technology for safety sensors and pilot assistance is purposefully gathered.
Instead of tradition and preindustrial craftsmanship, we defined the new premium,
a premium that left the convention of  leather, wood and chrome behind.
This will be the aesthetics of the electric age, high-tech minimalism that redefines
luxury for the sustainable decade.
We have pressing questions that need answers.
Clearly sustainability is not limited to the electric drivetrain.
Sustainability means on a much broader sense, from the very first step of
the production of the car, to the very end when you actually take care of what
is left of the car in the recycling process, to come to a fully sustainable
chain of mobility.
It’s a new era that has started and the Polestar Precept is a messenger
of what is to come, and a reminder that our journey has just begun.