Hi, I'm A. Jesse Jiryu Davis
and I'm going to tell you how Python coroutines work.
Little about me,
I work for a MongoDB,I'm a staff engineer, there work on the Python and the C drivers for MongoDB.
Yes, we are hiring and I highly recommend working for MongoDB.
You can go to Mongo-jobs to see all of the jobs that we've got open.
And if you want more information about this talk,
I've set up a landing pages at bit.ly/coroutines
You can find links there to the code that I'm going to write right now,
and also to a chapter in the upcoming architecture of open source applications book
that I co-wrote with Guido Van Rossum that goes into far more depth and is a very detailed exposition of python coroutines work.
So the agenda for this demo is going to be a
callback-based async framework,
and once we've written that we're going to see that it's very efficient but also kind of a mess,
and so we're going to adapt that to a coroutine based framework instead.
So to begin with a callback based async framework,
It uses non-blocking sockets.
uses the callbacks,
of course,
and it also uses an event loop.
And as for coroutines,
well, we'll cross that bridge when we come to it.
So a little bit of setup,
I've written a simple web server and.
It can respond to an HTTP request.
I wrote this for a local python conference PyGotham 2015,
so you can see that it says hello to all of the incredible people there.
And the other interesting thing about this framework is its kind of slow.
This web server returns very simple response,
but I've coded it so that it takes almost a second to reply.
And so that's going to end up being very important,
because that's the sort of thing that async is optimized for.
Is for talking too slow servers or slow clients efficiently.
So let's see,
how would we fetch a URL in the kind of typical python way.
so we would need to import socket right?
And?
Connected to the proper domain and port.
we format a request
then we would send it to the server.
And I'm going to do this in Python 3
and so it's important to encode everything that we're going to send over the wire.
Oh,
and the other important thing to remember is that.
Each HTTP requests end in a double carriage return to a new line
so once we've sent the request were going to receive the response and that'll come back to us in chunks.
so we're just going to collect those in a list.
Receive them up to a thousand chunks
a thousand bytes at a time,
and as long as we've got a chunk.
will append it to the list and if we get an empty chunk,
then we know that the server is hung up on us.
so our reception is complete,
and so the body is going to be....
We'll use the empty bye to join all the chunks.
And then we'll decode that.
The utf-8 by default.
And then let's just prints the first line of the body.
So,
and since we're in an infinite loop,
we need to return,
so that's our get function and if we get that path Foo
and if I run this, you'll see that the first line of the response is an http 200 OK.
And?
Let's also see.
How long that took
So it takes about a second because there's a little bit of overhead in the Python interpreter.
the problem with this approach is that if we want to get 2 Urls,
it's going to take two seconds because we get them serially.
And the typical approach to this might be to launch these two operations on two threads,
but that might become inefficient if we're waiting for hundreds of slow requests,
and we have to spawn hundreds of threads for them.
There's a lot of overhead though it's not necessary,
so we're going to try out making an async framework to do it instead,
so that we don't have to spawn hundreds of threads in order to do hundreds of slow i/o operations,
we want to be more efficient than that.
So.
A async framework could uses non-blocking sockets and in python making socket non blocking is very simple.
Now what's going to happen if we run this?
We're going to get an exception because.
A non blocking socket what that means is any operation that would block,
like connecting,either succeeds immediately or raises an exception.
Right.
It's not allowed to block.
it's not allowed to wait for success.
So we need some way to wait for that to complete.
And the way we do that in Python.
Well,
first of all,
we can just ignore that error.
But that's not going to get us very far
because as soon as we tried to send something of the socket is going to say that it's not connected yet right
because when we called connect,
the non-blocking socket began the operation.
But it didn't wait for the operation to complete.
And so we're not ready to send it yet.
So how do we know when we're ready to send an operation?
Well,
python 3.
There's this handy module called selectors.
In every operating system since time immemorial,
there has been some way to wait for some event on a non blocking socket.
Originally,
there was the system call select,
and then over time,
more and more scalable versions of select have been invented.
Like poll on Linux,
epoll on Bsd and Mac kqueue on windows.
there's these I/O completion ports.
The nice thing about Python 3.4
Is that you can just ask it for a default selector,
and it will figure out what your running and give you the most efficient selector for your platform,
so we'll make one of those and.
Before we try to send anything on the socket.
We're going to wait for it to be readable.
We're going to wait for it to be ready for something to be sent,
so to do that,
we register the sockets file number,
which is just an integer.
it's just a file descriptor.
And we're going to tell the selector that this is a file number that we're interested in events on
and the specific event that we're interested in is we want to know when the socket is writable
and pycharm can auto import that constant for us.
The next thing we do
so all we have done so far said I'm interested in this event on this file descriptor.
And then if we call select that will wait for some event that we've asked about to happen.
So,
once that happens,
we can unregistered the file number.
And by this point.
s is writable.
So that means that we can legally now call send on it.
So if I call this now.
You'll see that I get past this line,
but now we're throwing an exception down here because the socket is writable,
but it hasn't become readable yet We haven't waited for the server to start sending its response.
So in order to wait for that,
we have to do the same dance again,
and this time we're not interested in write ability we're interested in readability.
So we have the pycharm auto inputs that
We wait for it again,
and once this call completes,
then we'll unregistered the file number,
and now we're allowed to receive
so if I run this code now it completes,
but we haven't really won anything right still took two seconds.
We just kind of made a small mess in our code.
But we haven't gained any efficiency improvements yet.
So what's the next step?
The next step after we've started to use non blocking sockets,
is callbacks.
So I'll explain how that works.
Callbacks are a way of allowing multiple operations to be waiting concurrently for i/o operations.
To begin with, this get.
When it starts connecting,
it needs to register callback to be executed once the socket is writable,
and then it needs to return
so that work can begin on getting the other URL while we're waiting to connect this socket right,
we need some sort of concurrency in order to get past this two seconds.
So let's see how that would work.
We can begin by writing the body of that call back,
so I'm gonna call it connected.
This is going to execute.
Once the socket is connected and it's going to do the next step.
But the problem is,
you can see that right now PyCharm is sort of losing its mind
because there's two variables that are not bound in this new function because we created them up here in get.
And the two variables are s and request.
So let's say that those are passed into connected somehow.
And that somehow is going to be.
We're going to use a lambda to create a closure to capture those two values.
so we'll create a Lambda.
And we'll say that calling the Lambda executes connected with the socket and the request,
and we'll call this lambda callback.
Now what do we do with this callback?
Well selector.register,
it has this special hidden argument sort of a b-side,
and it's called data,
so we're going to pass the callback again as data.
because this is Python,
The data can be anything so we're going to pass in our lambda as the data.
And?
We're going to wait until connected is called to actually unregistered that file number.
Now,
if we do this.
Unfortunately,
we don't actually get any work done.
Because our callback is never actually executed.
So how do we make sure that this callback is actually run, once the event that it's waiting for has been executed?
Well for that we need the third part of our async framework.
We need an event loop.
so I'm going to code that down here.
get is going to run first and it's going to start a socket connecting,
and then it's going to register a callback to be executed when the socket is writable.
and once foo has done that it returns and bar does the same thing.
So now we've got to two non blocking sockets that are open and in the midst of connected,
and they've both been registered with the selector.
So I'm going to run a *dirt simple little event loop here,
and it's going to say selector dot select.
Now let's run this through the deBugger here and see what select actually returns.
So I set a break point,
and now we've got this events list,
and if I inspect that,
you'll see that it's a list.
It's got two elements,
and let's see what that first element is.
It's got.
It's a tuple with two values.
A second value isn't very interesting.
This is just the *mask that we passed in at first,
and it's equal to the EVENT_WRITE value.
but we already knew that because that was the only event that we were interested in.
It's this first element of the tuple.
This SelectorKey thing that's really interesting,
and you'll see that the data value that I passed in when I called register.
We're getting that back out in this events list and its contents is that lambda that I registered as the callback
So let's execute it.
So for event.
And mask events.
Mask is the thing we don't care about.
its too.
It's equal to EVENT_WRITE
but this event here.
Its data field is the callback that we originally registered
so I'm going to call that cb,
and then I'm just going to call it.
So if I run this now instead of breakpoint here and see what happens so it can step in.
And you'll see that we step into this lambda here.
And the lambda calls connected and connected is executed with the socket and the request,
which is get foo
So we run this.
We'll see that we need to do the same transformation down here for s.recv.
So let's do that.
And we can say.
The callback.
For when the socket is readable,
we're going to call it readable
and the same way that connected needed to take the variables that had been available in the previous callback as arguments so does readable
in this case still needs the socket.
It doesn't need request we're done with that,
but it does need the list of chunks.
So it's going to take those two as arguments,
and when it's executed,
it knows that s is readable by this time.
So we can unregister its file descriptor and receive a truck.
And we know that a chunk.
Well,
we know that this won't raise an exception because the select call.
Down here said that whatever we're waiting for on this socket is ready.
So we won't throw a resource unavailable or whatever that exception was.
The chunk will either contain something or if the server has closed,
the connection then chunk is empty.
And we know that we're done.
So up here,
that means that we don't call select,
because that's the eventloop's job,
but we do need to create the callback.
So it's going to be very similar to the callback that we created before
it's going to be a closure expressed by lambda,
and when we execute it.
We're going to pass it the socket and the chunks,
and this is no longer a loop.
We just register.
The callback once and then we're done.
And that means that,
since we no longer have a while true loop
that down here, if we have a chunk,
we need to wait for the remaining chunks,
so we can't just leave here.
We need to go.
Callback equals yet another closure,
and that's going to cause a second call or Nth call to this readable function again
and we'll register that again with a selector to re-register the socket that we unregistered up here
and then this return calls no longer necessary.
So if we run this.
We'll see that.
Both of our requests now complete.
So that's fantastic,
but unfortunately.
We don't see her final output because we're in this while true loop,
so were blocked here on this selector because there's nothing left to do,
but we haven't told the loop to complete,
and if we hit stop here,
we'll see that.
This line is, in fact,where we're stuck.
So I think that the right way to complete this loop now is to somehow figure out when all work is complete and then exit the loop.
So I'm going to say that there is some number of tasks.
*That are always in flight.
To begin with,
there are none.
And whenever we call get.
It'll Increment the number of tasks.
And when we have finished reading a response from a server.
Then it's time to decrement it.
So when we call get foo that increments the tasks to one
and when we call get bar, that increments it too,
and then,
as each of the chains of callbacks runs to completion,
it decrements n_tasks.
until this event loop sees that n tasks is zero and quits
If we run this,
then we'll see that both of the requests complete and miraculously it's only taken one second, not two.
and we can do.
Oops.
Many more of these concurrent requests and it will still only take one second.
And the reason for that is that the server is so slow
that this client is not spending significant CPU processing each of the responses
compared to how long its spending waiting for the next chunk from the server.
The server takes a full second to return just a few hundred bytes of data
and all the client is doing is appending those chunks to a list.
So the client is spending almost no CPU
with spending overwhelmingly the majority of its time waiting for i/o.
So,this is the sort of thing that async is optimized for.
We can do probably dozens or even hundreds of simultaneous requests with a simple framework like this one.
and not lose significant amounts of time on computation,
and it's very efficient because it doesn't have to hold open idle threads In order to do that.
So that's great.
It's very efficient,
but you'll also see that it's kind of a mess compared to a very simple initial implementation of Get,
we've now created a whole bunch of mess.
We now need three functions where
before we only had one.
These three functions.
What's particularly about about them is that each time a function exits,
it loses all of its local variables *right so s and request and chunks
each time one of these callbacks completes and registers the next callback in the chain to be executed.
It has to manually copy its state into a closure so that that state is available to the next call back in the chain.
The normal facilities that the language provides to us in a stack and in local variables,
we have to manually recreate that stuff in our async framework.
The language is basically no help to us here in terms of maintaining state across IO operations.
So the solution to this is the next phase.
It's coroutines.
And coroutines are built on Future.
Which is a class that we'll see in a second on python generators.
And on another class that we'll see in a moment called Task.
Now there are a bunch of kinds of things called coroutines.
coroutines are very old idea.
There are many kinds of implementations of coroutines in many languages
in Python3 asyncio
what we mean when we say coroutines is,
Generator based coroutines.
Greenlet are also called coroutines in Python3.5.
There are now new things called native coroutines that can take advantage of the new async and await keywords.
They're essentially syntactic sugar on top of generators.
So if you understand the discussion they were going to have right now,
you'll understand how the Python3.5 native coroutines work as well,
although they're built into the interpreter rather than built out of generators,
the way we're going to do right now.
So.
The first thing that we need is a future class.
And you'll see why in a little bit this is useful
but for the moment I'm just going to present it,
and you'll just have to trust me that this is going to be a useful thing,
so a future represents some pending event that we're were waiting for.
It has a list of callbacks that will be executed when that event occurs,
and when that event occurs, somebody's going to call resolve and the future will.
Execute all of the callbacks that were waiting for that event.
So that's our future class.
And we're going to do this simple transformation where instead of register and callbacks directly with the selector,
we're going to register futures instead.
So we add the callback to the list of callbacks.
waiting for this future to be resolved and instead of registering the callback directly.
We register the future instead.
And I have to do the same thing here.
And finally,
we have to do that same laborious transformation.
in the three places where we had registered callbacks,
we're now adding callbacks to futures and registering the future instead.
And that means that down here in our event loop.
The event that data is no longer a callback its future,
and so we don't call it directly.
Instead,we say future.resolve.
So, you can expect,
with such a simple transformation that had probably got it right,
and it looks like I did so.
All we've done so far is made our code even worse,  even more messy and long,
and we have simply got the same performance that we had before.
So the next step is going to be to somehow use these futures with generators to start to implement coroutines.
So I'm going to do a quick little refresher about Generators.
cause there's a few confusing things about them.
Even for veteran python programs.
So a generator is created with a generator function
and a generator function is any function that contains the yield statement.
So this generator function is going to print start yield one.
Middle.
Two.
And then it's done.
And the funny thing about a generator function is that when you execute it,
it doesn't actually run its code.
It didn't print start middle or done
Instead,it created a generator object
and this generator object contains a code object *that's the byte code that represents this stuff.
And?
It's got forty four bytes
and the generator also has a stack frame.
And that's got an instruction pointer,
and it begins his negative one,
meaning that it hasn't executed any instructions yet.
And that's why we didn't actually see any of these prints statements is being executed.
So the way to run a generator is to call him next on it.
And if you do that,
then you'll see that it executes its first few bites of byte code,
so it prints start
and one is actually the return value of the next statement
because the return value of next is whichever yield is next executed.
And the instruction pointer is now paused at thirteen bites into the forty four bytes of bytecode.
So if we call next again
this time,I'm going to assign its return value so that you can see that a prints middle.
But it returns two.
Which was the value passed into the next yield statement.
And now our stack pointer....
Sorry,
our instruction pointer is at twenty eight of forty four.
And if we call next one more time.
Then we'll raise stop iteration exception,
which indicates that
It's done executing and the lasti pointer has actually been deleted.
So that's how a generator works in all versions of Python going back two point five.
So how do we use that to create a coroutine?
Well,
here's the promise.
The promise is going to be that.
This get function.
Which currently has to create a closure that captures his local variables.
Names that closure callback.
adds that callback to the future and then registers that future with the selector.
This can be simplified to not require a call back at all.
So I'm going to delete the callback.
I'm going to delete the callbacks body.
But we need to pause until s is writable
somehow here before we unregistered it and then rely on the socket to be writable so that we can call send on it
and the promise is that somehow,
by yielding F,
the future that we just created.
Somehow we can pause this generator until the event that we said we were interested in has occurred.
And if we believe that this promise is true.
Then we can combine what had been two functions into a single generator function that contains a yield statement.
But the promise is not going to be fulfilled just yet because if I run this,
it's going to take zero seconds.
It has no output,
and it doesn't do any work.
So why is that?
What happened here?
Well,
recall that when you execute a generator function,
it returns a generator doesn't actually run any of its code.
So now that I've added a yield statement here to get,
that means that get here.
Just returns a generator.
doesn't actually do anything,
and the same here.
So how are we going to execute it?
How do we call next on it?
So that is the third piece of this puzzle of this coroutine based async framework is the task class.
Task class.
It's responsible for calling next on generators.
So let's see what that looks like.
And in the case of both future and task,
these are incredibly simple and oversimplified and buggy incomplete implementations of these ideas.
These ideas are fully expressed in a number of frameworks,
notably tornado and now in asyncio in the python3.4 standard library.
So my dumb version of the task class is going to look like.
We're going to initialize it with a generator.
I will save that.
And then we'll have a function called Step,
and this terminology is borrowed from a asyncio.
What step does his calls next on the generator.
it's going to yield a future.
So that's going to become the return value of next.
So let's capture that.
And then.
What do we want to happen when this future is resolved?
We need to add some kind of callback to the future,
something that we want to happen once the future is ready
and let's just pass self dot step in as the callback.
So once this future is resolved,
we'll just come right back into here and we'll call next and self.gen again.
when we call next on self.gen again,
that's going to resume here.
And therefore we know that we can unregister the sockets file number,
and that s is now writable.
So if we run this still not going to work.
The reason for that is.
That we need to make an initial call the self.step,
so that we make an initial call to self.gen so that we get the get function started,
and it will connect the socket and so on.
So let's just do that right here.
In the constructor.
And then the final step of this conversion is going to be down here,
where we need to wrap each of these calls in a task
so when get returns a generator, the task wraps it
Signs it to self.gen and calls self.step
and that will call next and that will actually begin this thing executing up until the first yield statement
So if I run this.
In a way,
you will see the way we make progress.
Because we raise a stop iteration exception here.
So that that actually that's good news,
because it means that this get generator has actually been run to completion.
It's done the work that it set out to do.
so.
if we.
Catch that.
What do we want to do here?
Well,
the task is done.
So let's just return.
And if we execute this version.
It actually completes.
So this is fantastic now we've still got a few stray callbacks.
So.
We can get rid of those the same transformation that we did here.
So we're just going to do it down here again as well,
so we're going to.
We don't need this call back any more.
You don't need to add it to the future.
We do still need to say what event we're interested in and register the future to be resolved when that event occurs,
but we can delete the callback definition.
Since we're still in the same function as we were in before,
we don't need a redundant global statement.
And if we simply yield this new future that we created,
that means that.
By now,
by the time the task resolve.. resumes us,
the socket is now readable.
And here we've got our last of the callback.
so we can delete that.
And we can yield our future instead of registering a callback.
What do we want to do once we have received the next chunk?
In other words,
once the socket is readable again?
we want to receive the next chunk right？
so what we're going to end up doing is
we're going to end up reproducing the same while true loop that we originally had in the olden days at the beginning of this talk,
when we were writing a simple blocking get.
So that's going to look something like.
We're going to put this within the loop.
And each time through the loop we say,
I want to read from the socket,
so wait for this future to be resolved.
And then unregistered the socket from the selector.
get the chunk.
And if there is any then added to the list and this stuff is now extra.
The loop will just repeat and do that stuff again up here,
and if there's no chunk.
That means that.
We're done reading the server response,
and so we can.
Join the body up,
print the first line decrement the tasks count,
and since now we're in an infinite loop again.
here we need to return as soon as we're done.
Now,
if all goes well and I run this,
then it still takes one second.
it still does all the work that it was asked to do
and we can still scale this out to a large number of tasks without any loss of performance,
because launching ten fifteen coroutines is incredibly cheap,
it's roughly as cheap as a bunch of callbacks.
So coroutines are kind of the best of both *worlds.
they're about as cheap as callbacks they're much cheaper than threads
on my system, I measured that a coroutine takes...
About six K of memory versus about thirty K of memory for a thread,
and furthermore I did a little experiment and found that I was capable of launching over a hundred thousand coroutines.
Their limited only by the amount of ram that the Python process is allowed to allocate.
versus Threads,
which are subject to other limits beside simply memory limits.
There are various user and operating system limits on the number of threads that a *process is allowed to start with.
which are difficult in various ways to work around,
and they take up space and operating system data structures and the operating system scheduler
that eventually causes their overhead to become quite significant.
All they're doing is waiting around for some sort of slow IO operations that aren't actually going to require very much CPU。
so compared to coroutines for a application like this,
that's going to spend very little time doing computation
and overwhelmingly spending its time waiting for a slow server or a slow client at the other end of the socket.
Coroutines are much more efficient for this kind of thing,
but compared to call backs their lot simpler because.
You can put all of the code for a coroutine in one function,
so you don't have to declare and register a whole chain of callbacks.
And you can just reuse your local variables the same way that  you have always done.
So that's the beginning of Tornado style or async i/o style coroutine based async framework.
So if you want to know more about this,
go to bit.ly/coroutines so I've have created a landing page for you there
that'll link you out to a version of the code that I wrote just now,
as well as link you to a chapter that I wrote with Guido van Rossum
that will appear in the next book in the architecture of Open source Application series.
and that chapter goes into far more detail about how generator based coroutines are implemented in asyncio on Python3.4 standard library,
and especially it goes into how coroutines take advantage of generator features that are specific to python3
and how a asynchronous queue class that's included in asyncio,
can be used to coordinate coroutines in a way that's very familiar to people who are used to using threads.
And as a reminder,
if you want to work with people like me at a opensource company,
that's very warm and diversity has really fulfilling and technically challenging jobs.
Mongo db is hiring.
We have offices in New York in Palo Alto and worldwide.
Go to bit.ly/mongo-jobs.
I would love to work with you.